Guide to the Nathan Whiting Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Nathan Whiting papers
1705-1828
MS 552
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.75
(4 boxes)
The papers consist of family correspondence of the Whiting family as well as the personal correspondence of Nathan Whiting, military and legal documents and miscellaneous family papers, including an address by Polly Whiting on the importance of education for women (undated), an essay by Samuel Whiting on his marriage (pre-1725) and a plan of the Township of Cumberland showing land belonging to Colonel Nathan Whiting and others..
Whiting, Nathan, 1724-1771
Custodial History
Gift of Minnesota Historical Society, 2006 and 2011.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 1942.
Existence and Location of Copies
The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 2006-M-099 and 2012-M-007, is available on microfilm (389 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM 110.
Arrangement
Arranged in four parts and two additions: I. Correspondence. II. Wrtitings and Legal Papers. III. Miscellaneous and Unidentified. IV. Oversize.
Biographical / Historical
NATHAN WHITING, 1724-1771
Nathan Whiting, the youngest of thirteen children of the Rev. Samuel and Elizabeth (Adams) Whiting of Windham, Connecticut, was born in that town, May 4, 1724, being a brother of Colonel. John Whiting (Y. C 1726) His father died when this son was 16 months old, and when he was in his 14th Year, his mother married the Rev. Samuel Niles (Harv. 1699), of Braintree, Massachusetts. Nathan Whiting was mainly brought up by his sister Mary, and her husband, Rector Clap.
He studied at the College for two years after graduation, and then settled in New Haven as a merchant, but accompanied as Ensign the Connecticut troops in the expedition against Louisburg in 1745; in this service he so distinguished himself, that at the end of the campaign, a lieutenancy in the British army was given him by Sir William Pepperrell. A little later he was in business-partnership with Thomas Darling (Y. C 1740). While in this employment the French war began, in 1755; and he was appointed, in March of that year, Lieutenant Colonel of the 2d Connecticut Regiment. He assisted in garrisoning Fort Edward; and on September 8, was with Colonel Ephraim Williams in the detachment sent against Baron Dieskau. On the fall of Williams, the command devolved on Lieutenant Colonel Whiting, who conducted the retreat of the corps with a skill and coolness which did him high credit. When the next expedition was sent out in 1756, he was promoted to a Colonelcy. He continued in the service throughout the war, and was esteemed by both British and Americans an officer of uncommon merit.
In 1769 and 1770 he was a representative of New Haven in the General Assembly; and at the time of his death he was in nomination for the Upper House.
He died in New Haven, April 9, 1771, at the age of 47. His estate was inventoried at £1322.
He married, July 12, 1750, Mary, daughter of Captain Rosewell and Mary (Haynes) Saltonstall, of Branford, her mother having married Rector Clap in 1741. Of their five sons and four daughters, three sons and one daughter survived infancy; the eldest of these children was graduated here in 1777. The widow of Colonel Whiting next married the Rev. Warham Williams (Y. C. 1745), of Northford Parish, in North Branford, Connecticut, whom she survived.
President Dwight thus describes Colonel Whiting: "He was an exemplary professor of the Christian religion; and for refined and dignified manners, and nobleness of mind, has rarely been excelled." His portrait is in the rooms of the Connecticut Historical Society, at Hartford.
AUTHORITIES.
Conn. Journal, Apr. 19, 1771 Dwight, "Statistical Account of New Haven", 75. Goodwin, Genealogical Notes, 333, 336-337. Kingsley, Hist. Discourse at New Haven, 68. Larned, Hist of Windham County, i, 564. N. H. Col. Hist. Soc. Papers, iii, 608. Pease and Niles, Gazetteer of Conn. and R. I ., 206.
Franklin B. Dexter, Biographical Sketches of the Graduates of Yale College, 1701-1745 (New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1885), pp. 750-751.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of family correspondence of the Whiting family as well as the personal correspondence of Nathan Whiting, military and legal documents and miscellaneous family papers, including an address by Polly Whiting on the importance of education for women (undated),an essay by Samuel Whiting on his marriage (pre-1725) and a plan of the Township of Cumberland showing land belonging to Colonel Nathan Whiting and others.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 2006-M-099 and 2012-M-007, is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 110 instead of the originals.
Armed Forces; Marriage; Women -- Education; Connecticut; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1754-1763; Deeds; Soldiers; Clap, Mary, 1703-1769; Whiting, Nathan, 1724-1771; Whiting, Polly; Whiting, Samuel; Williams, Mary Saltonstall Whiting; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1743
- Inventory, 1705-1828; .50 linear feet (1 box, 1 folio)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Patrons must use microfilm (FILM HM 110) instead of the originals.
  - Correspondence
    - Amherst, Jeffrey, 1st baron Amherst, to Nathan Whiting (typescript), 1762 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Brattle, (Mrs.) K., to Mary (Haynes) Saltonstall Clap, 1738 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Clap, Mary (Haynes) Saltonstall), to Nathan Whiting, 1756 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Eliot, Jared, to Nathan Whiting, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hale, Elisha, to Mary (Saltonstall) Whiting Williams, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hale, George, to Elisha Hale, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hale, George, to an unidentified brother, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hale, Thomas, to an unidentified brother, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Irwin, [J.L.?], to Elisha Hale, 1805, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jones, Betsey, of Wilkes Barre, Pennsylvania, to her uncle, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Saltonstall, Rosewell, to Mary (Haynes) Saltonstall Clap, 1734 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Whiting, Nathan
      - to Mary (Haynes) Saltonstall Clap, 1760, 1762, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - to James [Fitter?], requesting appointment as collector of the port of New London, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - to Sir William Johnson (photostat), 1768 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - to Roswell Saltonstall, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - to Mary (Saltonstall) Whiting Williams, 1747-1763, undated (Box 1, Folder 13-21)
    - Whiting, Samuel, to Warham and Mary (Saltonstall) Whiting Williams, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Williams, Mary (Saltonstall) Whiting, to Nathan Whiting, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Writings and Legal Papers
    - Hale, Elisha, of Glastonbury, Connecticut: deed to Nathan W. Hale of Glastonbury, Connecticut, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Lucas, Samuel, of Middletown, Connecticut: deed to Sarah Haynes of Hartford, Connecticut, 1705 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Saltonstall, Roswell: deed to his sisters, Mary (Saltonstall) Whiting Williams and Katharine (Saltonstall) Wells, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Seymour, Timothy, of Hartford, Connecticut: miscellaneous papers, 1777-1798, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Whiting Nathan
      - Obituary for Samuel Whiting (copy of newspaper article), 1753 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Military papers re: enrollments and expenditures, 1755-1760 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
      - Inventory of his estate, [1771?] (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Whiting, Nathan, family: vital records, with remarks about mortality, [1756-1771?] (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Whiting, Polly: address on the importance of education for women, Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Clap, Thomas, "Meditations on the Death of My Wife" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Scope and Contents
      Manuscript, unsigned, by Thomas Clap on the death of his wife. Includes a manuscript annotation in an unidentified hand stating that the manuscript was written by Samuel Whiting. A more complete version of the Clap manuscript is available in Thomas Clap, President of Yale College, Records (RU 130), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
    - Williams, Mary (Saltonstall) Whiting: inventory of her estate, [1801?] (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified
    - "An Elegy of the Death of Miss Elizabeth Saltonstall", Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "A Cattelouge of the Books Given to Roswell from his Honrd Father", Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Invitation to a "Ball, in Celebration of Peace," in Wethersfield, Connecticut, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Oversize
    - Whiting, Mary: letter to her mother, Mary (Saltonstall) Whiting Williams, 1780 (Box 2)
    - Whiting, Nathan: "A [Relation?) of Provision Money due to the Tenth Company of the [2nd?] Conn. Reg. Commanded by N. Whiting Esq, from the Time of Enlistments to the Time of Receiv. King's Provis.", Undated (Box 2)
    - Whiting, Nathan, and Mary (Saltonstall) Whiting Williams: photographs of portraits, Undated (Box 2)
- Additional Material, 1760; Accession 2006-M-099
  This accession consists of an order book presumably kept by Nathan Whiting while on a march with British and Colonial troops from Lake Ontario in New York to Montreal, Canada, during the French and Indian War. Information is given on routine army matters, camp life, deserters, court martials, inspections, and the surrender of Montreal by the French to the British.
  - Order book, 1760 June 8-November (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional Material, 1770; Accession 2012-M-007
  - Township of Cumberland plat map, 1770 (Box 1)